בוקר טוב, Boker tov, good eighth day of the עומר, Omer, first
day of חנוכה. Chanukah. We pick up with
last line of yesterday's דף Daf is פ"ח. Pei-Chet. We pick up
with the last line of פ"ז עמוד ב'. Pei-Zayin Amud-Bet. We're dealing
with the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah has a debate of the
חכמים Chachamim and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Somebody says their under-age son
to buy something in the store. The storekeeper gives the kid the
oil in a jug and the change and then it all breaks
and gets lost and so on. So according to the חכמים, Chachamim,
it's the storekeeper's liability because it was never stopped being the storekeeper's
money or his oil because the kid couldn't do a קניין, kinyan,
couldn't acquire it. And we interpret the sending of the kid as
just placing the order. But then it's the storekeeper's responsibility to make
sure it gets to the father in a responsible way, in a
protected way. Whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said no, implicitly the father
was saying send it back with the kid and the father was
assuming responsibility. All right, so that was all very nice. The question
though that we had was what's the story about the liability of
the jug? Why should the storekeeper be liable because we assumed that
the jug was the father's jug? So why should the storekeeper be
liable? So so far the best answer we had was רב Rab
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that said no, that the, I'm sorry
who was it, רב Rab and רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? I believe
so.
No, sorry, רב Rab and רב יוסף, Rab Yosef, excuse me, that
said it was the storekeeper's jug. So it's the same story as
with the oil and with the change. It's all the storekeeper's stuff
that he's giving to the kid. The גמרא Gemara had a problem
with this with the end of the משנה Mishnah although simply the
end of the משנה Mishnah was saying that if it's the kid's
jug, the end of the משנה Mishnah says if the jug is
in the kid's hand the storekeeper is exempt. So they would have
read it if it's the father's jug, the kid's jug, then the
storekeeper is exempt on the jug. Very easy read of the משנה.
Mishnah. I have no idea. I have no idea. Maybe the גמרא
Gemara just wanted to explore other possibilities. I'm serious. Sometimes the גמרא
Gemara doesn't accept something not because there's a real problem but because
it wants a way of presenting other possibilities. So but the גמרא
Gemara rejected it. It
wanted to read the end of the משנה Mishnah that it was
still the storekeeper's jug and then there couldn't be an explanation why
it should matter whether it was in the kid's hands or not
the kid's hands. So we're still trying to explain this משנה: Mishnah:
why is the storekeeper,
if it's the father's jug, why should the storekeeper be liable? So
now we go back to so we give a third possibility. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא אביי בר אבין, Ela Abaye bar Avin,
end of פ"ז עמוד ב', Pei-Zayin Amud-Bet, רבי חנינא בר אבין, Rabbi
Chanina bar Avin, דאמרי תרוייהו, De-Amrei Tarvaihu, so apparently these two brothers
said הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what we're talking about כגון
דנטלה למוד בה. kegon de-natla limod bah. So that similar to an
answer we had yesterday that the storekeeper was taking it in order
to check out whether he wanted to buy it and that made
him a borrower on it. Here he is taking it without asking
permission, but the kid brings the jug, it's the father's jug and
the storekeeper says oh you got a jug, here before I give
you your oil, let me borrow it so I can go ahead
and measure out some oil for the other customers or something like
that. Okay. Yeah, it doesn't sound like it's specifically for him. And
therefore it's a case of שואל שלא מדעת. shoel shelo midat. So
that would be a way in which the storekeeper would assume liability.
And then the end of the משנה Mishnah would read: if it
was still in the kid's hands, meaning if the storekeeper never borrowed
it, then he's exempt on the jug. But if he took it
from the kid's hands in order to use it for himself and
he's a שואל שלא מדעת, shoel shelo midat, I don't know if
it's obvious, anyway let's take a look. וכדרבא, U-che-de-Rava, let's take a
look.
וכדרבא U-che-de-Rava דאמר רבא de-amar Rava הכישה וחייב בה, hikishah ve-chayav bah,
that if somebody was you know,
here was a case about a what do you call it, somebody
who saw an animal and he's an older person and it was
not considered, it was beneath his dignity to return it, so he
didn't have an obligation of השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, but if he
actually hit it and had it move, so then in order to
return it, then he does become responsible and then he does accept
the responsibility. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, I'm sorry, so hold
on, wait a minute, hold on, let me remind myself.
Okay, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. I jumped ahead. The case about
borrowing it and שואל שלא מדעת shoel shelo midat we're going to
get up to in a minute. We haven't introduced the idea yet
of שואל שלא מדעת. shoel shelo midat. So Michael, that answers your
question. At this stage, we're assuming that maybe the father was still
okay with the storekeeper using it. Okay. So the storekeeper took it
to use it to measure out the oil for the kid. And
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, but as soon as he takes
it he becomes liable and responsible for it, which is a little
funny because he's only taking it for the sake of measuring it
out for the kid, not for his own
purposes, so he specifically is asked to do it by the owner.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to reject it, okay, and
then it's going to get onto what I said, הכא דרבה דאמר
רבה הכישן נתחייב בה *hacha d'Rava de'amar Rava hikeishan nischayav bah*, that
if you hit the animal to return for an אבידה *aveidah*, you
become responsible for it even though you don't really have an obligation
of השבת אבידה *hashavat aveidah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to
sort of be saying that once you sort of get it in
your hand, even if you're doing it on behest of the בעל
הבית *ba'al habayit*, you somehow become liable for it. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* rejects this. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute, אימא
דאמר רבה בבעלי חיים *eima de'amar Rava beba'alei chayim*. When is that
true that you become responsible, okay, even though you don't have like
a מצוה *mitzvah* of השבת אבידה *hashavat aveidah* just because you took
it, even without a מצוה *mitzvah* of השבת אבידה *hashavat aveidah* you're
responsible? That's if it's an animal and you started to get it
to move. Why? Because once you started to get it to move,
דהא אנקיטהו נגרא ברייתא braita *deha ankiteihu nigra brayta*, you've made it,
you've sort of made it step outside. Once you started getting it
to move, now it won't necessarily hang out where it was. There
it was, it was grazing in the meadow, you thought you were
going to be a צדיק *tzadik* and return it even though you're
not obligated, you hit it in order to bring it to town.
Once you started getting it to move, who knows where it's going
to wander off to now? So therefore now you become responsible because
if you don't do anything you'll be negligent in the fact that
otherwise it would have stayed there grazing in the meadow. Okay. What
does נגרא *nigra* steps, ברייתא *brayta* outside. It means you took it.
You took it, yeah, you made it take steps outside. So that's
where even though there's not a מצוה *mitzvah* of השבת אבידה *hashavat
aveidah*, you have liability because you've now been negligent, if you don't
do something now it's going to get lost. Okay. כי האי גוונא
מי אמר *ki hai gavna mi amar*, but in this case if
you're just using it at the owner's request, behest, so why should
you be liable for using the owner's jug to pour oil for
the owner? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא אמר רבה אני
וארי שבחבורה *ela amar Rava ani ve'ari shebachabura*. So רבא *Rava* says,
I and the lion amongst us, who is that? תרגמינהו *targumineihu*, we've
explained this, and מאן ניהו *man nihu*, who is that other person?
רב זירא *Rav Zeira*. הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha b'mai askinan*, what's the
case? כגון שנטלו למוד בו לאחרים *kegon shentalo limod bo l'acherim*. Right,
so I had jumped ahead. So you took it without permission to
use it for measuring out for other people, okay, and therefore ובשואל
שלא מדעת shelo madaat קמיפלגי *u'v'sho'el shelo mida'at kamifligi*. The debate is
somebody who borrows something without asking permission. All that is right, correct,
all that, but again it's reading it in contrast to the last
line where it's still in the hands of the kid. So rather
than reading it whose jug is it, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying no, no, no, the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* emphasizes in whose hands
was it. So if you never took it out of the kid's
hands you're exempt on the jug, if you took it out of
the kid's hands you're liable. Why would that be? So it's understanding
taking out of the kid's hands means and using it to your
purposes and therefore you're a שואל shoel שלא מדעת shelo madaat, *sho'el
shelo mida'at*. Okay, ובשואל שלא מדעת קמיפלגי *u'v'sho'el shelo mida'at kamifligi*. מר
סבר שואל shoel. הוי *mar savar sho'el havi*, you're a שואל shoel.
*sho'el*, ומר סבר גזלן gazlan, הוי *u'mar savar gazlan havi*, you're a
גזלן gazlan *gazlan*. Now the question is, who cares whether you're a
שואל shoel. *sho'el* or a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan*? Okay, you gave it
back, and if you say is it broken, you're אונס ones, *ones*,
well a שואל shoel *sho'el* is חייב chayav, *chayav* in אונס *ones*.
So the question is, what is considered you've done your responsibility of
returning a borrowed object? Okay, and there's a difference between a שואל
shoel. *sho'el* and a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan*. A שואל shoel. *sho'el* does
his
responsibility once he sort of returns it to the place he got
it from. So even though in the hands of the kid it's
not protected, that's considered
he's now discharged his responsibility, he's returned it to the kid, he
got it from the kid. So if he's just a שואל shoel
*sho'el* returning it to the kid, he's done. But if he's a
גזלן *gazlan* he has a heightened responsibility because you can understand this,
right? A שואל shoel *sho'el* has liability, a גזלן *gazlan* actually took
it from the owner and has
to basically, made the owner lose the object. It's no longer in
the possession of the owner. It's not just a question of liability.
So in order to return it you have to fully restore it
to the owner. So therefore you have to give it back to
the owner and you have to give it back in a way
that the owner sort of, it's protected and not into the hands
of the kid. Okay. Now this doesn't exactly, give it back to
the father then, to the father exactly. Okay. Doesn't a שואל sho'el.
*sho'el* have to
fully
restore it also? So according to this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, all a
שואל sho'el, *sho'el* has to do is return it to the state
in which he took it from, because a שואל sho'el *sho'el* the
question is that he's liable. It's not that if I borrow something
from you it's not like you now have your cow no longer
is taken away and your property is now lacking a cow, and
now I have to make you whole again. That's not the idea.
I borrowed something, it's not that it's sort of taken away from
you, it's just I have liability. So the question is, when does
my liability end? So my liability ends when I restore it to
the state in which I took it from. But what's the difference
with a גנב *ganav*? Because the גנב *ganav*, it's not enough to
restore it from the state he took it from, you have to
restore it in a way that it is under the owner's control
and it's protected. So the גנב *ganav*... In this case when it
was taken from the kid, that was its initial state, but that's
not a protected state. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot points out that even
though a גזלן, we have a principle that a גזלן שלא מדעת
can do השבה שלא מדעת, hashavah shelo madaat, that if you stole
something without the owner knowing, you can return it without them knowing.
Okay, so I pickpocketed you and I stole your wallet, and then
I had a moment of remorse and I went ahead and I
bumped into you again and I stuck your wallet back in, and
you didn't know that I took it. You know, לא ידע בשכבה
וקומה, lo yada beshichvah uvekumah, even though I took it, you don't
know I returned it, I'm יוצא. yotzei. But that's so you don't
need the owner to know about it, but I returned it to
a protected place. Here, it's not a protected place, so you didn't
make the owner whole again.
Even though you took it from an unprotected place. Right. So that
would be the debate. Now of course then it's a completely coincidental.
Rabbi Yehuda and the Rabbanan debate about the oil and the and
the change, you know, about a question about whether the kid is
just placing an order or it's implicit you should send it back
with the kid. And their debate about the jug is a completely
different debate. The debate about the jug is whether when you borrow
the jug שלא מדעת, are you a שואל sho'el, or גזלן, and
do you exempt yourself when you give it back to the kid?
Okay, but that at least the end of the mishna now means
if you never took it from the kid, then you're everybody agrees
you're exempt on the jug. Okay, so now the Gemara says like
this. Okay, so we ended with that, that seems to be how
we're happy to explain the mishna, although I prefer Rabba and Rav
Yosef. So now the Gemara says גופא, gufa, let's now look at
that statement of שמואל Shmuel that we had before about if you
borrow something in order to check it out to consider buying it,
then you're considered a שואל. sho'el, So גופא, gufa, אמר שמואל, Amar
Shmuel, הנוטל כלי מן האומן לבקרו, hanotel keli min hauman levakaro, you
took a vessel in order to check it out. Now again the
question means what does it mean check it out? Does it mean
just hold up an apple in the store to see if it
has any blemishes, or does it mean you took a car for
a test drive? Okay, the second one clearly you should be considered,
or whatever, not clearly but it makes sense that you're a שואל.
shoel The first one a lot less. Okay, ונאנס בידו venenas beyado
and some some accident happened, חייב, chayav you're חייב chayav because that's
considered like you now become a שואל. Now there's a whole debate
of תוספות Tosafot's and the רשב"ם Rashbam whether the implication is you
become a שואל or you become a לוקח. lokeach. Like if I'm
checking out this apple and I want to sort of, you know,
I don't know, check it for for blemishes, is it like I
picked it up for because I'm thinking about buying it, so it's
like I've already bought it, you know, but with like a with
like an asterisk that if I see that there's a problem I'm
going to want to return it. That's one way of reading it,
but you're essentially already like a לוקח. lokeach. And the other possibility
is you're not a לוקח, lokeach, you're a שואל. You're borrowing it,
you're taking it under your control for your interests because you want
to see if it's okay or not okay. And therefore you're a
שואל. So both of those would be חייב chayav. in a case
of an אונס, but there might be other ways in which there
would be a difference whether you're a borrower or a purchaser. So
let's take a look. Okay, the Gemara is not clear which one
of those two models שמואל Shmuel is working with. By the way,
if you break
it, you know, if you break it you own it. Right, but
that's true whether you're a שואל or a לוקח. lokeach. Right, the
question is what and not even if you break it, right, even
if it's an accident, if it breaks you own it.
Right. Exactly.
Exactly. So והני מילי vehani mili דקייצי דמיה. dekaitzi dameha. That's only
if the price is fixed. Right, if you know like this is
a dollar a pound, or you know, five dollars for you know,
for this thing or whatever. Now because you need the price to
be fixed, it sounds like the model we're working in is that
you're like a לוקח. lokeach. You're a purchaser with a right to
return it, because if it was just that you were borrowing it
to determine if it was good and if you wanted to buy
it, why did you need the price to be fixed? You know,
because because the price to fix means you know, maybe in the
end you'll you'll you won't buy it anyway because it's going to
be too much. Okay, but I'm still borrowing it now to check
if I want it or not. So it's it seems more logical
that the model here is not שואל but you're a type of
a לוקח. lokeach. Let's keep on going. Okay, so קייצי דמיה kaitzi
dameha means that for instance, you
know, let's understand, like you go to the shuk, they say these
are eight dollars a pound. And you know you're going to haggle,
it's not going to be eight dollars a pound. I don't know,
that I don't know. Okay, or did you actually come to a
final agreement? No, no, I think it means that you it starts
with a fixed price, but I don't know how to deal with
that fixed. Okay, ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, now another case. So a
certain person went into a butcher's house, a butcher store. אעול לבי
טבחא. aul lbei tivcha. אגבה אתמא דבישרא, agbah atma devisra, he picked
up a side of meat. Okay, and to check it out to
see if he wanted to buy it, how fresh it was, how
good it looked, how fat it was. Okay, ובהדי דקאגבה, uvehadi dekaagbah,
as he was lifting it up, אתא פרשא ata parsha מירמא מיניה.
mirma mineh. Came a פרשא, parsha, whatever they have there, horseman. That's
what I thought, פרשים. parashim. Right, okay. Came a horseman and took
it from him. Okay, now אתא לקמיה דרב יימר, ata lekamei deRav
Yeimar, so he came to Rav Yeimar, חייביה לשלומי דמיה, chayveh leshalumei
dameha, he made him pay based on שמואל. Shmuel. You picked it
up to check it out. Here we see it's not just like
a car that you're driving around the block. You're not using it,
you're just checking it out. And nevertheless you become liable.
והני מילי vehani mili דקייצי דמיה, dekaitzi dameha, and that's only if
the price is fixed, like we said before. Ten dollars a pound.
Exactly. ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, now another case. The person who's liable
to pay for it? The guy who picked it up to check
it out? Not the guy who then ran off with it. Well,
that's some non-Jew, you're not going to get it back from him.
That's a separate case. Yeah, I mean, he's a גזלן, but if
you get it back from him because ההוא גברא דאייתי קארי לפום
נהרא. Hahu gavra de-aitei kari le-fum Nahara. A certain person brought some
gourds to this place, פום נהרא, Pum Nahara, literally means the mouth
of the river. Anyway, אזלו כולי עלמא שקול קרא קרא. azlu kulei
alma shakul kara kara. Everybody came and everybody started grabbing the gourds
and looking at them and deciding if they were going to buy
it. And here he was, he was afraid he was never going
to get his gourds back. You know, a hundred people mobbed him
and everybody's looking at the gourd. Like, I'm not clear that they're
actually planning on stealing it, but he's afraid he's never going to
get them back. He can't control the situation. So אמר להו, amar
lehu, so he made an announcement. He said, הרי הן מוקדשים לשמים.
harei hen mukdashim la-shamayim. Okay, if I'm not going to get it,
you're not going to get it either. So therefore he says, I'm
being מקדיש makdish it all to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. He
can do that, right? Because he's the owner. Well, that's the question.
Were they still under his control? Okay, so אתו לקמיה דרב כהנא,
atu lekamei de-Rav Kahana, came to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. אמר להו
אין אדם מקדיש דבר שאינו שלו. amar lehu ein adam makdish davar
she-eino shelo. You can't sanctify something you don't own. Which means that
it's a case of—which by the way is תוספות's Tosafot evidence that
we're not dealing with—that the person is not a שואל. Because if
your liability when you pick it to inspect it is that of
a שואל, then I can be מקדיש makdish something that you've borrowed,
that you're a שואל on. So it sounds like everybody who's picking
it up to inspect it is a לוקח lokeach even before they've
paid the money. You know, a לוקח lokeach with like, as I
said, an after-use that they can choose to return it. You know,
and I can also choose to void the sale, right? Meaning, he's
still got to pay the guy. It's not like it's
not—I'm a לוקח, lokeach, I understand. Right. But it's still not his.
Right. So it's not his. While they're picking it up and inspecting
it and planning on buying it and determining whether to buy it
or not, they are temporary לוקח lokeach and therefore the owner is
no longer the owner and is no longer in a possibility position
to be מקדיש. makdish. Now, I don't know exactly because if Michael
comes ahead and takes my apples inspecting it, the same way he
can decide in the end not to buy it, can't I also
decide in the end not to sell it to him? Meaning, even
if you say he's like a temporary לוקח, lokeach, you would sort
of think that both of us have a right to back out
on that, right? I mean, we've just got through spending how many
דפים dappim determining when does the קניין kinyan take place, right? There
has to be, you know, a fixed price and there has to
be a מעשה קניין ma'aseh kinyan and whatever. I mean, I have
to have דעת da'as to sell it to you. Is it assumed
that as soon as you pick it up, I have דעת da'as
to sell it to you? So, you know, it's funny. If it's
true that we can both back out, then I'm not sure why
I can't מקדיש makdish it. Why don't we read my being מקדיש
makdish it as implicitly like I'm backing out and being מקדיש makdish
it? So it's not so clear to me exactly what the logic
here is. I don't know about the הקדש hekdesh things, but didn't
we read somewhere that you can מקדיש makdish something that you think
you're going to have in the future, that you're planning to have?
Well, that depends on רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and מקדיש דבר שאינו
שלו, makdish davar she-eino shelo, right, but you know, yeah, but this
would be different because it's not like if the people keep it,
he's not going to have it in the future. It's not something
that's, I mean, you know, if they decide they're going to go
through with the sale then he's not going to have it in
the future, so I don't think it fits with that model. Like
a Schrodinger's thing, it's like either they—yeah, I know, right? Exactly, exactly.
So I don't know, I don't really fully understand this.
והני מילי הוא דקייצי דמייהו. ve-hanei mili hu de-kaitzi dameihu. The גמרא
Gemara makes it fit with the previous model: that's when there's a
fixed price, אבל לא קייצי דמייהו ברשות מראיה קיימי ושפיר אקדיש. aval
lo kaitzi dameihu birshus mareihu kaimei ve-shapir akdish. But if not, then
it still is in the control of the owner and it was
a good הקדשה. hakdashah. But again, if it's a שואל, תוספות Tosafot
says there's no logic why you can't מקדיש makdish it if it's
a שואל, so תוספות Tosafot says this is proof that they're קונים,
konim, that they're considered to have bought it, but presumably with the
right to return it. But again, I would imagine that the owner
would also have a right to void the sale if that's the
case. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. הלוקח
ירק מן השוק ובייר והניח אפילו כל היום כולו לא קנה ולא
נתחייב במעשר. ha-lokeach yarak min ha-shuk u-viyeir ve-heniach afilu kol hayom kulo
lo kanah ve-lo nitchayev be-ma'aser. So here you are, this is a
question about a חבר chaver who is buying from an עם הארץ.
am ha-aretz. So a חבר chaver who buys from an עם הארץ,
am ha-aretz, you know, somebody who's not scrupulous in תרומות ומעשרות, terumos
u-ma'asros, so if you actually take the stuff and bring it home,
you have to be מפריש דמאי, mafrish demai, you have to be
מפריש mafrish like תרומות terumos and—well not תרומה, terumah, but anyway,
מעשר ma'aser out of ספק safek or rabbinic מעשר ma'aser known as
דמאי demai because you can't be certain that the עם הארץ am
ha-aretz took it. So the question is here I am, I'm at
the עם הארץ's am ha-aretz store and I'm checking out the vegetables
and I'm looking, nah, that's got a blemish, nah, don't like that,
feeling the pineapples, making sure they're ripe, I'm putting it down, I'm
spending my whole day doing this. Okay, if I was sort of
קונה koneh and returning it, קונה koneh and returning it based on
the model that we just said, then as soon as I was
קונה koneh it, I had a חיוב chiyuv to be מפריש תרומות
ומעשרות. mafrish terumos u-ma'asros. So then how could I go ahead and
return it to him? I'm not allowed as a חבר chaver to
take something that I own that I have a חיוב chiyuv to
take תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-ma'asros and give it to an עם הארץ
am ha-aretz without taking תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u-ma'asros. So how—if we have
this purchase model, how is this going to work? So it says
like this, let's take a look. הלוקח ירק מן השוק ובייר והניח
אפילו כל היום כולו לא קנה ולא נתחייב במעשר. ha-lokeach yarak min
ha-shuk u-viyeir ve-heniach afilu kol hayom kulo lo kanah ve-lo nitchayev be-ma'aser.
You don't... take possession and you're just checking it out. גמר בלבו
לקנותו, Gamur b'libo liknoso,
if when you picked it up you were planning on purchasing it,
קנה ונתחייב במעשר. kanah v'nischayev b'maaser.
Okay, then you are obligated. So this seems to be that it's
working on the previous model but introducing what is a logical next
step, that next criteria that we haven't mentioned, which is it's not
enough that I'm looking at your apple in the store, I'm actually
picking it up and saying I am going to buy this if
it if I find it without a blemish. So you needed that
גמר דעת g'mar daas which again makes sense if we're dealing with
a קניין kinyan model, not a שואל model which seems evident, then
when you take it, you're not just checking it out and being
tentative if you're going to buy it, that's why you need it
כקציצה דמיהו. k'ketzitza damaihu. כקציצה דמיהו, k'ketzitza damaihu, you're still tentative. So
you have to know what the price is and you have to
have in your mind, I'm going to buy this if there is
no if it's like what if it looks the way I want
it to look. Okay. So you assume by the action of picking
it up and looking it out what is כוונה. kavanah. Well that's
exactly. So that's a good question too. Yeah, that's a good point
too. Like, right, I mean you're right, like in this case which
is about the חבר chaver and דמאי, demai, it's up to that
guy's own conscience, but in these other cases, it seems like we
were assuming that was their intent. That's a good point. Right, I
mean how do we know the guy with the chicken thing he
wanted that piece of meat, put it back? And I have to
tell you, I still don't really get it. Like even if I
want to buy it if there's no blemish, why does it mean
I'm buying it now and I have a right to return it,
rather than I'm not deciding yet to buy it until I see
that it looks like the way I want it to look? But
anyway, that's the model we're working with. So if he's intending to
buy it, you know, assuming that there's no problem, okay, then he's
got a problem, everything he picks up he owns it, how could
he return it to the עם הארץ? am haaretz?
So, so the ברייתא says להחזירו אי אפשר, lehachziro ee efshar, to
just give it back to the עם הארץ am haaretz he can't,
שכבר נתחייב במעשר. shekvar nischayev b'maaser. He's obligated to מעשר, maaser, you
can't just give back the whole pineapple like the way it is,
okay, because he's חייב. ולאסרו אי אפשר, v'le'asro ee efshar, now you
can't go ahead and like, well okay, I'll first cut off a
piece of the pineapple תרומות ומעשרות trumos and maasros and then I'll
give it to you, שכבר מפחית בדמים, shekvar mafchis b'damim,
you're making it worth less, you're, you know, you're taking away some
of the fruit. So what are you going to do? So I
mean maybe you have to buy it. So הכיצד, ha keitzad, so
how do you deal with this? מעשרו ונותן לו דמי מעשר. maasro
v'nosun lo d'mei maaser.
So you take מעשר, maaser, cut your slice of pineapple off, and
you pay him for the part of the pineapple that you took.
In my example with the pineapple you probably have to pay him
more because now the whole pineapple is going to go bad. Okay
now תוספות Tosafot. points out that it's really not an issue about
דמי מעשר d'mei maaser because the הלכה halacha about דמאי demai is
once you're מפריש mafrish מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, okay, מעשר ראשון maaser
rishon can be eaten by a non לוי. Levi. It's only a
דיני ממונות dinei mamonus issue. And since you don't know if you
owe it or not because maybe the עם הארץ am haaretz already
took it, then you say to the לוי, Levi, המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. The same is true with a מעשר
עני. maaser ani. If you take מעשר עני, maaser ani, then you
say to the, then the thing is no longer טבל. tevel. You
want your מעשר עני, maaser ani, prove to me that the עם
הארץ am haaretz didn't already take it, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'ayah. So actually, מעשר ראשון maaser rishon and מעשר עני
maaser ani you actually can just say I'm מפריש mafrish this section
of the pineapple as מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, this section is
מעשר עני maaser ani and you and you can give it back
to the store owner, you don't have to take it away, המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. The problem is if it's
a מעשר שני maaser sheni year because then it's קדוש kadosh and
you have to eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim or be פודה. podeh.
And within the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon the problem is תרומת מעשר.
trumas maaser. That you have to separate out and can't, can only
be eaten by a כהן. Kohen. Okay, so because of that, basically
you have to, you take what you need to take and you
pay him for it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אטו משום
דגמר בלבו לקנותו קנה ונתחייב במעשר? atu mishum d'gamar b'libo liknoso kanah
v'nischayev b'maaser? So just because you planned to do it, you now
are obligated, which is such a funny question because isn't that what
we've been talking about all this time? Okay,
so you know, so I mean the רשב"ם Rashbam says אמאי אפילו
כקציצה דמיהו יכול להחזירן ולהדרינהו ולהיפטר. amai afilu k'ketzitza damihu yachol lehachziran
v'lehadrinhu u'lhipater. You can return them, so presumably what that means is
is that you know, if in the end you choose to return
it, somehow you never owned it in the first place, but it's
like it's so strange, but then why were you liable a minute
ago? Like make up your mind, either you are קונה koneh it
or you're not. But anyway, now all of a sudden the גמרא
Gemara doesn't doesn't understand that you're קונה. koneh. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב הושעיא הכא בירא שמים עסקינן, Amar Rav Oshaya, hacha
b'yarei shamayim askinan, we're talking about a פרום frum person. That's a
great answer. That's a great answer. Another... you could have a חבר
chaver who isn't a ירא שמים. yarei shamayim.
You mean implicitly you could have a חבר chaver who isn't a
ירא שמים. yarei shamayim. Well, yeah.
Okay, כגון רב ספרא דקיים בנפשיה ודובר אמת בלבבו. k'gon Rav Safra
d'kayem b'nafsheih v'doveir emes bilvavo. And since, you know, so once he's
agreed this famous story with רב ספרא Rav Safra he was saying
שמע Shema and somebody came to him to ask him to buy
something and he was sort of like not paying attention to the
guy and the guy kept on raising the price and raising and
raising the price and then when רב ספרא Rav Safra finished שמע
Shema he said, okay fine, I'll give it to I couldn't interrupt,
I was saying שמע, Shema, but I had always intended to sell
it to you at the original price, so I'm going to do
the original price. Therefore sort of because you know so even though
he could obviously have accepted the higher price, he wanted to do
what he sort of had originally intended. So how's that relevant here?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says: והכי נמי גבי מקח כיון דירא שמים
הוא כיון שגמר בלבו זכה במקח ונתחייב במחיר וכי מחזיר כחוזר ומוכר
לו דמי. vehachi nami gabei mekach keivan deyerei shamayim hu keivan shegamar
belibo zacha bamekach venitchayev bamechir vechi machzir kechozer umocher lo dami. Since
I had planned on buying the pineapple when I picked it up,
it's like I bought it and therefore I want to treat it
as if I bought it, I do what I had intended, and
therefore I have an obligation to be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish terumot
uma'asrot. But again I just find this very strange. How does this,
why did the—what? Is the previous case also a ירא שמים? yere
shamayim? No, no, the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to be. So how
is this, why is the גמרא Gemara bothered here and not before?
It sounds like according to the גמרא Gemara that you are a
קונה, koneh, but if you decide not to buy it and the
thing hasn't had an accident happen, it's in its original state, right,
then you could essentially be retroactively never have been קונה. koneh. You
return it. But if something happens to it, it seems like, right,
because you have to understand, what is this מציאות? metziut? I'm picking
it up to inspect it, I'm a לוקח, lokeach, but I can
change my mind. So where the גמרא Gemara comes out at the
end is it sounds like if I change my mind, then I
was never קונה. koneh. But if an accident happened before I changed
my mind, then I'm not able to give it back in its
original state, then I'm stuck in my position of having been קונה
koneh it and I have to reimburse the owner.
Right. Of course again the funny thing is that if it's all
that tentative reality, you would think the owner could be חוזר chozer
as well and gets to that whole question about being מקפיד makpid
etc. Yes, Charlie? We learned with this that someone who is ירא
שמים yere shamayim can do business with an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz.
There you go. Okay, as I understand this as well, if he
does it correctly, he's
מחזיר machzir with the agreement of the מוכר. mocher.
Well, he said—wait a minute—that problem—right,
meaning well the question is if he's ירא שמים yere shamayim like
the רב ספרא Rav Safra case, so then why doesn't he just
go through, go through what he really planned? Meaning rather than returning
it and giving the תרומות ומעשרות, terumot uma'asrot, if you picked it
up with the intention to buy it, then buy it! Right. So
says okay, but the owner says it was okay to return it.
Yeah, that's good. Right, correct, I think a comment matches תוספות. Tosafot
All right, let's take a look now at the next משנה. Mishnah,
Now we move on from—yes? Isn't this considered a particularly special characteristic?
Isn't it just something that anybody should do? If they pick something,
they, you know, and they need to return it, and they took
something off of it? But they didn't take something off of it,
meaning if you had never bought it, it was never like you
bought it, if you returned it and then retroactively you never bought
it, you never have a חיוב chiyuv of תרומות ומעשרות. terumot uma'asrot.
So why do you have to do anything? You pick up the
pineapple, you put it down.
Right? The whole question is by being this ירא שמים, yere shamayim,
it's because I picked it up with the intention to buy it,
I have to treat it as if I bought it and I
have to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumot uma'asrot. But if I never treated
it as if I bought it, or if by returning it it's
retroactively like I never bought it, right, then I have no obligation
to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumot uma'asrot. But I didn't hurt the owner,
I just picked it up and I put it down. Okay. All
right, so now that now we move on to the next משנה,
mishna, and now we move again, there's a progression here, right? We
dealt with the acts of purchasing, we dealt with the issues about
when can you back out and if you deliver the wrong object,
and then we dealt with things which are like about making sure
the person gets everything he's fully entitled to, you know, dripping out
the last drips of the of the oil that you're pouring out.
And then we had another case of oil with the kid and
who's liable. And now though this is I think most similar to
the discussion before about those drips to make sure he gets every
bit that you bought from him, is the issue, the basic issue
about just weights and measures and making sure that you're actually giving
the person the full amount that the person bought. Okay, so let's
take a look. הסיטון, hasiton, which is a, you know, this is
like a middleman, the רשב"ם Rashbam says: הוא חנוני גדול שקונה הרבה
יחד ומוכר לחנונים קטנים. hu chanvani gadol shekoneh harbeh yachad umocher lechanvanim
ketanim.
You buy from the producers and you sell to the—what? Wholesale? Yeah.
הסיטונאי, hasitonai, what does הסיטונאי hasitonai mean in Israel? Whatever, like wholesale,
middleman, yeah, a wholesaler. Right. So it's a different story.
Tell you
later. Okay.
Okay.
All right, so and now the רשב"ם Rashbam claims that it's the
Greek word, that it's the Greek word for wheat. So I don't
know if that's true or not. What does, what does Steinsaltz say?
From the Greek sitones, meaning a commissary for buying grain, referring to
one who sells produce in large quantities. There you go. Okay, so
you have this wholesaler. מקנח מדותיו אחד לשלשים יום. mekaneach midotav echad
leshloshim yom.
So he has to clean out his vessels, you know, from making
sure that there's no residue that remains, because if there's residue in,
you know, in the vessel, so you have your, you know, your
one liter vessel and whatever it is, you know, so if there's
residue then you fill it up and you pour it out, you're
not giving the person the full amount that they bought. איפה ואיפה.
eifa ve'eifa. Exactly.
So איפה ואיפה eifa ve'eifa might be that you actually intentionally are
using a lighter weight when you... when you sell than when you
buy, but here it's just keeping it clean, okay, because if you
don't keep it clean, the person isn't, might not be any like
malice, but the person isn't going to get the full amount that
they bought. Okay, so once every 30 days. ובעל הבית אחד לשנים
עשר חודש. U'ba'al habayit echad l'shneim asar chodesh. But a, the, you
know, a homeowner, which is like somebody that just sells, I mean
the question is where's the middle person, the standard חנוני, Chanvani, okay,
which is what we're going to get to. The homeowner is the
person that like isn't even in the business, occasionally I sell stuff
out of my house. So in that type of a case, you
know, it's very, it's used a lot less, so you have to
clean it a lot less. The assumption here is, the more you
use it, the more there's residue. Okay, oh it's meant I didn't
have to do the dish, I can do the dishes once. Yeah,
exactly, very good. Tell your wife that. Okay, anyway, okay, אחד לשנים
עשר חודש, Echad l'shneim asar chodesh, once a year. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר חילוף הדברים. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer chiluf hadvarim. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says it's the reverse. He says that, you know,
that the more something is used, the more it stays clean because
I don't know, and where some, where if it's used rarely, whatever
residue stays in it adheres. So actually the less frequently it's used
the more you have to clean it out. Okay, חנוני מקנח מדותיו
פעמים בשבת. Chanvani mekaniach midotav pa'amayim b'Shabbat.
Now how about the storekeeper? Okay, he's the person that has the
sort of, you know, is obviously regularly using it. So here it
is twice every week, okay, much more than the סיטון. Siton. This
seems to be going like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, that the
more frequently you do it, the more you have to clean it
out, so the storekeeper's like using this every single day with multiple
people. Okay, וממחה משקלותיו פעם אחת בשבת. U'memache mashkelotav pa'am achat b'Shabbat.
And wipes down, so that's his like his containers, okay, to make
sure there's no residue and he also wipes down his weights once
a week because now the, I'm sorry, okay, I apologize. Okay, so,
so, you know, you put your weights down and maybe I don't
know some dust or other types of things, you know, adheres to
it and then it's not the accurate weight. Of course, it's only
a problem if it weighs too much, if it's the weights you're
using for buying. If it's the weight you're using for selling, then
you're just benefiting the buyer, right? Because you have a balance. So
if this thing which represents a pound weighs 1.01 pounds and I
put it down and I'm selling you my apples for a pound,
you're getting more, right? So if you're cleaning it, it obviously means
that there's some residue, you know, dust or who knows dirt that's
attached that makes it weigh a little more. So it is interesting
though, you know, because it could, it's not clear whether that hurts
him or, you know, or doesn't, but somebody is getting an unfair
deal. Alright, so anyway, you have to clean that once a, once
a week. Okay, now that's less than, you know, stuff that you're
constantly filling up my liter container and pouring it out and filling
and pouring it out, that's going to get more residue attached to
it, so that's twice a week. But this which is just sitting
around and we're just talking about dust, that's once a week. ומקנח
מאזנים על כל משקל ומשקל. U'mekaniach moznayim al kol mishkal u'mishkal. But
how about the other side of the balance? Where you actually put
the fruit? Okay, now if it's apples it's one thing, but if
you put wheat on the other side of the balance, right, and
you put the flour, so stuff starts to adhere to it. Okay,
it's sort of like the, it's sort of like the container that
I'm spilling out. So I'm regularly using this balance, and if stuff
adheres to this side, then the buyer is going to be cheated
out, right? Because then there's a little, it already weighs something before
I put my stuff on it. So in that case you have
to do that between every single weighing, you have to wipe it
down. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Said
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, במה דברים אמורים, Bameh d'varim amurim, when is
this true? בלח, B'lach, that if you're, that if we were dealing
with things that contain liquid, then there's more, there's more stuff that
adheres and so on. אבל ביבש אינו צריך. Aval b'yavesh eino tzarich.
If it's dry you don't have to. Now you understand like the
case I gave about the apples, right? Why would you have to
weigh, you know, clean it out if you're weighing apples?
Now flour might be well, I don't know, if flour sticks if
it's very fine, so flour might more be like לח, Lach, but
he means something that adheres. We'll see exactly what the line is
between that. Okay. What? כגון בשר דבר לח לא? K'gon basar davar
lach lo?
In the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
Oh yeah, the רשב"ם Rashbam says, right, כגון בשר ויין ושמן. K'gon
basar v'yayin v'shemen. So I assume the בשר Basar meant because there's
moisture on the meat. Right, it doesn't mean the meat itself is
lach but there's moisture on it. Something that's going to adhere to
the scale. That's how I understood it. Okay, that there's moisture. Okay.
וחייב להכריע לו טפח. V'chayav l'hachria lo tefach. Now, so that's keeping
everything clean and the right weight. Now, let's say, okay, I go
ahead and I weigh out for you your pound of apples. I
don't know if you've ever been in this, I mean when I've
bought stuff in the שוק, Shuk, okay, and sometimes actually here in
New York, you know, they have these like little fruit stands or
whatever in New York city, you buy something, after you buy it
and it weighs it out correctly, they like throw on a little
bit extra. Okay, so this is what this is saying, that this
was assumed to be the standard, that the storekeeper would throw on
a little bit extra to make sure that you're getting the full
weight. But. The what I don't really understand is the amount it
says is a טפח. tefach. I mean, that's a lot, right? A
טפח tefach is like four inches. So here you
are I wouldn't think the same thing would be true if you
were buying gold, okay? Anyway,
here's your scales, right?
Right? So here's my one pound weight, here are my apples, they
exactly weigh the same. I have to put on so many apples
that this now tips down a whole
טפח tefach from the even point. To me that seems like a
heck of a lot
of extra. Especially if it's a litra. Right. So the רשב״ם Rashbam
says, thank you, so the רשב״ם Rashbam says והמאזניים מצד הבשר טפח
שיהיה בשר שקול יותר
מן הליטרא. v'hamoznayim mitzad habasar tefach sheyihye basar shakol yoter min halitra.
So he says we'll see that in the גמרא Gemara but it's
talking specifically that it's a ליטרא. litra. What's a ליטרא? litra? I
think it says here pound. A pound. Okay, I still think that
if I'm buying twenty pounds and you say a טפח, tefach, it's
one thing. But you're buying a pound, a טפח tefach to me
it seems, now if the scale is very sensitive, if it's a
hyper-sensitive scale, a little bit of a difference will cause a big
movement. But a טפח tefach to me seems like a real lot.
I mean it's like three inches. Yeah, it would have to move
down. Yeah, about three inches. If it's a very sensitive scale, I
know, but I don't understand, to me that seems like a heck
of a lot. Okay.
השוקל עין בעין, ha-shokel ayin b'ayin, now, let's say because we're going
to see, because this is just when it's the custom to give
a little extra to put on a little extra, then the standard
is a טפח. tefach. Okay, but in other places the custom is
to do
no, precise, עין בעין, ayin b'ayin, like you see it looks exactly
even. So if that's the case,
נותנין לו גירומין. notnin lo gerumin. What you do is you give
the person, I don't know what the actual origin of this word
is, okay, you give like a little bit extra, alright, so meaning
as opposed to tipping the scales, no, you weigh the scales and
they're exactly even and you give the person what they bought and
it's sort of like a baker's dozen, then you throw in one
extra, what? A few grams. A few grams. Oh is that גירומין?
gerumin? I don't know Charlie what does it say גירומין gerumin means?
Does it say? Amount. Amounts, whatever. Okay. But the point is rather
than
measuring it based on creating an uneven balance of the scale, no,
you give the person the exact amount, you put everything in their
bag, and then you throw in an extra apple, okay? So what
is this גירומין? gerumin? So אחד לעשרה בלח ואחד לעשרים ביבש. echad
l'asarah b'lach v'echad l'esrim b'yavesh. So it sounds like what this is
is an extra
ten percent for liquid measures and twenty percent for dry measures. The
גמרא Gemara is going to actually say it's one out of ten
out of ten liters. So the גמרא's Gemara going to actually say
it means
one percent for לח, lach, and then it's going to have a
question whether this means one out of two hundred or one out
of four hundred for dry. So the גמרא's Gemara going to read
this a lot less, not ten percent but one percent. Okay, but
if it's only one percent, again, I still don't understand four טפחים.
tefachim. That seems to me a heck of a lot more than
one percent. Anyway, okay. מקום שנהגו למוד בדקה לא ימוד בגסה בגסה
לא ימוד בדקה. Makom shenahagu limod b'dakah lo yamod b'gasah b'gasah lo
yamod b'dakah. Now let's say that I basically use small measures or
big measures. So when I'm going to measure out, because what we're
going to find out is when I measure for you, okay, like
would I
normally smooth off the top of the measure, but do you get
a little bit of a curve on the top? What's that called,
the meniscus? No, or the meniscus is the opposite. The meniscus is
what goes down. No, the meniscus goes up. No, the meniscus goes
down I think is the curve anyway. Depends
whether the level is beneath the top. Oh, so if I overfill
it the meniscus. Oh, okay, so it is a meniscus. Okay, fine.
Alright, I was right. Okay.
Anyway, I give you a little, so if I am measuring with
small measures, for each measure I'm going to give you a little
bit extra to be safe. So the assumption is that when I'm
giving you with small measures,
you'll be better off than if I do with one big measure.
So in the place if the custom to use small measures you
shouldn't use big ones, big ones you shouldn't use small ones, because
somebody is going to lose out if you change the practice, either
the seller or the buyer. למחוק או לגדוש לגדוש לא ימחוק. Limchok
o ligdosh ligdosh lo yimchok. If the place is to smooth out
the top of the measure, then you shouldn't put extra on top.
If you put it, because I mean the buyer will be happy
but it's not fair to the seller. And if the place is
to put extra on top, then you shouldn't smooth it out.
Alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara we'll go
through this one by one. Yes. I think it's interesting the רשב״ם
Rashbam says that what is the
גירומין? gerumin? Yeah. גירומין gerumin is from הגרמה hagramah like in שחיטה.
shechitah. Oh right, to yeah right right right. Interesting use, right? I
mean I don't know if it's true. To bow, to tippo, to
tip, right. הטיה *Hatayah*, right? Right, right, right. הטיה *Hatayah* of the
שחיטה *Shechita*. Yeah. Why would
be these two, why one place does a little and another doesn't?
So it seems like it's a, it's a, it's not an individual
store, but like a locale. That what's the custom in the locale?
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will discuss why changing it would be
a problem, like if both sides agree. No, that I understand, but
I mean how would that develop to be uniform? That's what I'm
trying to do, equal weights and measures. Yeah, so if you understand
that different communities have different practices, you know? All right. מנא הני
מילי *Mena hanei milei*, where's this from? אמר ריש לקיש אמר קרא
*Amar Reish Lakish amar kra*, so where's this from that you need
to, you know, to we assume we're skipping the first part of
the משנה mishna *Mishna* about cleaning your stuff? Where's it from that
you have to add a little bit extra, you know, tip the
scales a little bit? So דאמר קרא אבן שלמה even shleima, וצדק,
צדק משלך ותן לו *damar kra even sheleima v'tzedek, tzedek mishelcha v'ten
lo*. Be extra righteous from your own, you know, give a little
of your own stuff just to make sure that the person is
getting everything they deserve. So that's the idea that you should give
a little bit to tip the scales. ואי הכי אימא סיפא, היה
שוקל לו עין בעין נותן לו גירומין *v'eichi eima seifa, haya shokeil
lo ayin b'ayin notein lo geirumin*. So if you're doing it exactly
precisely, then throw in a little extra. ואי הכרעה דאורייתא d'oraisa *v'ei
hachra'a d'Oraita*, and it's because אבן שלמה *even sheleima*, right, is about
the weighing process itself. So if you're reading this פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*
really literally, not just saying oh give a little extra to be
safe, but if you're reading it in the weighing, you should do
it in a way that's completely making sure the person gets extra
in the act of weighing it itself, so then the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says היכי יהיב ליה עין בעין *heichi yahiv lei ayin b'ayin*?
How do you ever allow for a practice of even if you're
going to throw in something at the end, if you're going to
read the פסוק *pasuk* to say that in the act of weighing
you always need to tip the scales in favor of the buyer,
then how do you ever have a practice of doing an accurate
weighing, of doing an equal weighing? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אלא רישא במקום שנהגו *ela reisha b'makom shenahagu*, fine. It's not talking
that there's a דאורייתא *d'Oraita*. I mean still maybe the principle that
you should give a little extra to be safe is דאורייתא *d'Oraita*,
but the idea that how do you do that? Do you do
that by tipping the scales, you know, or do you do it
by throwing in something at the end? That's based on what the
custom, what the convention is in that place. וכי איתמר דריש לקיש
אסיפא איתמר, היה שוקל לו עין בעין נותן לו גירומין *v'chi itmar
d'Reish Lakish aseifa itmar, haya shokeil lo ayin b'ayin notein lo geirumin*.
That when you're doing it precisely, you throw in something extra at
the end. מנא הני מילי *Mena hanei milei*? אמר ריש לקיש אמר
קרא וצדק, צדק משלך ותן לו *Amar Reish Lakish amar kra v'tzedek,
tzedek mishelcha v'ten lo*. So now notice we don't start with אבן
שלמה *even sheleima*. It's not in the act of weighing itself, it's
a more general principle: you're selling something, give a little extra that
you don't that the person hasn't bought just to make sure they're
getting the full amount. Okay, and that presumably translates into one of
two ways: either when you're doing the weighing, make sure that the
scale tips a little bit beyond the even measure, or no, measure
it at the even measure and then throw in something afterwards. Yeah,
but Charlie, something here is that it's always better for the buyer
to get more, but that's not true.
What do you mean? Why would I not want an extra apple?
Because then I have to deal with throwing out the extra food.
Oh. If you're a construction company, you get extra construction materials, you'll
have to have the expense of disposing of them. I hear you.
I assume we assume that it's such a small amount that it's
not going to be a טירחא *tircha*, that it's just going to
be a playing it safe amount. If I'm ordering a hundred two-by-fours
and I have ten extra two-by-fours... Yeah, but we're not dealing with
things that are number, right? We're dealing with things that are measured
and weighed. So a little extra to be safe, but I hear
the point. Okay, anyway, אמר רבי אבא בר ממל *Amar Rabbi Abba
bar Mamal*... Did you want to say something Rabbi Dov? I just
wanted to say is this, are we saying ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
is saying that גירומין *geirumin* is דאורייתא *d'Oraita* at this moment? I
think what he's saying is that some form of giving him something
extra is דאורייתא *d'Oraita*. Right, but not just leading it in the
limited sense of the tipping of the scales. Right. אמר רבי אבא
בר ממל אמר רב *Amar Rabbi Abba bar Mamal amar Rav*, ותן
לו *v'ten lo*. וכמה גירומין *v'chama geirumin*? How much is it? Because
I mean the משנה *Mishna* says אחד לעשרה בלח *echad
l'asara b'lach*, but now we're saying this because we want to reread
the משנה *Mishna*. אמר רבי אבא בר ממל אמר רב, אחד מעשרה
בליטרא בלח לעשרה ליטרין *Amar Rabbi Abba bar Mamal amar Rav, echad
me'asara b'litra b'lach l'asara litrin*,
if you're buying ten liters. Okay, so they add in a word
extra, לעשרה *l'asara*. אחד לעשרה לעשרה בלח *echad l'asara l'asara b'lach*.
One tenth if you're buying ten. Ten things, you know, so one
tenth of one unit if you're buying ten units. So it's a
very creatively read, but you know maybe the גמרא *Gemara* also felt
that it sounds like way too much in the משנה *Mishna* to
read it as ten percent. אחד לעשרה בלח ואחד לעשרים ביבש *echad
l'asara b'lach v'echad l'esrim b'yavesh*. איבעיא להו *Iba'ya lehu*, so if that's
how you read the first part of the משנה *Mishna*, how do
you read the one twentieth of the dry measure? היכי קאמר? היכי
קאמר, אחד מעשרה בלח לעשרה דבלח *Heichi ka'amar? Heichi ka'amar, echad me'asara
b'lach l'asara d'v'lach*. One tenth of one unit if you're buying ten
units of liquid. ואחד מעשרים ביבש לעשרים דיבש *v'echad me'esrim b'yavesh l'esrim
d'yavesh*, and one twentieth of a unit if you're buying twenty units
of dry, which would mean one four-hundredth, a quarter of a percent.
או דלמא לא, אחד מעשרה לעשרה דבלח *o dilma lo, echad me'asara
l'asara d'v'lach*, a tenth of a unit for every ten units of
liquid, ולעשרים ביבש *u'l'esrim b'yavesh*, and for twenty units of dry. So
it would be 1/200th, a half of a percent. תיקו. By the
way, I don't know why a dry measure you should give the
guy less of a of
a of a list throw in less than for a liquid measure.
Is it because we assume dry measures are more likely to be
precise than liquid measures? Is it because I really don't know why
it's different. Okay. אמר רב לוי, Amar Rav Levi, קשה עונשן של
מידות, kashe onshan shel middos, now that we're talking about this principle
of, right, being very scrupulous. Okay, it's funny we skipped over the
first part of the משנה, which really is like the
דאורייתא of אבן שלמה, you know, and you know, איפת צדק, eifat
tzedek, to make sure it's clean, it's accurate. Here we're talking about
the act of giving, you throw in extra. But how about the
actual weights and measures themselves? That was the first part of the
משנה we sort of skipped that over. But now we're going to
talk about that sort of more generally. And again, these are based
on פסוקים. pesukim. But now we're going to sort of talk more
like in a מוסר mussar context before we move back to the
פסוקים. pesukim. Okay. קשה עונשן של מידות יותר מעונשן של עריות. kashe
onshan shel middos yoseir me'onshan shel arayos. The punishment of being—this is
very important, right, for all the people—like they, you know, obviously that
problem that we've been dealing with for a few millennia, you know,
about how people treat the ritual laws more weighty than the בין
אדם לחבירו bein adam l'chaveiro laws. Right. So here the גמרא says
the punishment for transgressing, you know, unfair weights and measures, right, is
more weighty than transgressing the prohibitions of the עריות. arayos. שזה נאמר
בהן אל, shezeh ne'emar bahen eil, את כל התועבות האל, es kol
hato'eivos ha'eil, it says by the עריות, arayos, וזה נאמר בהן אלה,
vezeh ne'emar bahen eileh, and by the—and by the מידות middos it
says, what's the פסוק? כל עושה אלה כל עושה עול. kol oseh
eileh kol oseh avel. Okay, so אלה eileh is weightier than אל.
eil. So the גמרא says, מאי משמע דהאי אל קשה הוא, mai
mashma dehai eil kashe hu, and how do you know אל eil
means that it's like weighty?
דכתיב, dichsiv, ואת אילי הארץ לקח, v'es eilei ha'aretz lakach, the strong
ones of the land. So rather than saying it means these or
those, it's saying that this is weightier, and then so an extra
saying it in a bigger word, אלה eileh means even weightier. So
now the גמרא says,
גבי עריות נמי הכתיב אלה, gabei arayos nami haksiv eileh, what do
you mean? There's a word אלה eileh by the עריות arayos it
says
also? כי כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו. ki kol asher
ya'aseh mikol hato'eivos ha'eileh venichrasu. So the גמרא says, אלא אלה, ela
eileh, ההוא למעוטי מידות מכרת. hahu l'ma'utei middos mikares. No, that's saying
האלה ונכרתו. ha'eileh venichrasu. You only get כרת kares if you do
one of the עריות, arayos, like, you know, adultery or if the
woman is a נדה niddah or like incest or whatever. That's כרת,
kares, or worse. That and only עריות, arayos, only אלה, eileh, not
for מידות. middos. Even though מידות middos is more—is weightier, but you
don't get כרת. kares. So the גמרא is saying now you're telling
me it's not כרת, kares, why is it weightier? ואלא מאי עדיפיהו,
ve'ela mai adifayhu, in what way are they weightier? דהתם אפשר בתשובה
והכא לא אפשר בתשובה. dehasam efshar bitshuvah vehacha lo efshar bitshuvah. Because
when you steal from weights and measures, right, it's not like stealing
from one person. If you're overcharging, you're overcharging every single person that
goes into your store. So then if you want to do תשובה,
tshuvah, how are you going to return to everybody? You know, it's
really fascinating, the guy who like one of the guys who was
head of like Crazy Eddie's. People remember Crazy Eddie's?
Right. Eddie Antar. Yeah, he died. He was Jewish. Yeah. So anyway,
so it was a whole scandal, and one of the guys like—he
really felt deep remorse for it, and he spent the rest of
his life like going and going to high schools and lecturing kids
about honesty in business and like trying as much as he could.
But you're never going to find everybody you cheated and return to
them. I mean the גמרא says, you take money and you buy
צרכי רבים, tzorchei rabbim, you make some contribution to the community. Right.
But you never fully, you know, are able to fully make good.
Now, now the question is, what do you mean by the עריות?
arayos? Right, עריות, arayos, what type of עריות arayos are we talking
about? Like if we're talking about like somebody slept with a married
woman, right, so that impacts her—you know, her status with her husband.
If you're talking about there's a kid, the kid's a ממזר. mamzer.
So if you take a look at
תוספות—right, Tosafot, I mean, physiologically, right, I mean, you know, exactly, like,
seems like most of the עריות arayos cases are also not fully
reparable. So what are we talking about? So—so if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot he says, התם אפשר בתשובה ודוקא בעריות שאין בהן ממזרות.
hasam efshar bitshuvah vedavka ba'arayos she'ein bahen mamzeirus.
So first תוספות Tosafot, says if there's no ממזר mamzer that results,
no child. אבל הבא על אשת איש והוליד ממנה בן או שאר
עריות שיש בהן ממזרות זה מעוות לא יוכל לתקון. aval haba al
eishet ish veholid mimena ben o shear arayos sheyesh bahen mamzeirus zeh
me'uvas lo yuchal liskon. This is something—this is a perversion that cannot
be fixed, כדאמרינן k'd'amrinan whatever, ואי אפשר בתשובה. v'i efshar bitshuvah. Okay,
so that seems pretty reasonable. And then we're saying even more than
that, right, even if it's not a child, like what does it
do? You know, what you happened, you now slept with—a man sleeps
with a married woman, what does that now do to her relationship
with her husband? Other scenarios. Incest, clearly, even if both sides are
willing, you know, could be very psychologically, you know, damaging. רב חיים
אומר, Rav Chaim omer, אע"ג דמעוות לא יוכל לתקון מכל מקום אפשר
בתשובה שציווה לו הקב"ה דלא ציווה אלא לעשות לו תשובה. af al
gav d'me'uvas lo yuchal liskon mikol makom efshar bitshuvah shetziva lo hakadosh
baruch hu d'lo tziva ela la'asos lo tshuvah.
Between you and God, right, he says, it could be you're right.
You're not going to correct the damage done in this world. But
God says if you do an עבירה, aveira, do תשובה. tshuvah. So,
and if it's an עבירה, aveirah, so you've done תשובה. teshuva. Okay,
but but אבל גזלן שתשובתו הוא שיחזיר הגזילה כדכתיב והשיב את הגזילה
והיכא דגזל רבים ואינו יודע למי ישיב אף על גב דיעבד צרכי
רבים לאו תשובה מעלייתא היא. aval gazlan sheteshuvato hu sheyachzir hagezeila kichtiv
vehashiv et hagezeila veheicha degazal rabim veino yodeia lmi yashiv af al
gav deyatze tzorchei rabim lav teshuva maalyasa hi.
So it effectively means עריות arayos also you could do lasting damage.
Okay, but what the תורה Torah says is the way you do
תשובה teshuva meaning to make it right with God, not necessarily to
make it right for the people, you know, is just repent. Whereas
by when you steal, part of the תשובה teshuva process is giving
the money back, and that you'll never be able to do. Of
course the problem is if you've actually hurt people through your sin
of עריות, arayos, then it's not just between you and God, it's
between you and the person, right? And that also requires making the
person whole. So it's not really such a satisfying answer. I mean
there's very obviously there's profound ways as we know, you know, today,
it's recently been in the New York Times recently, right? This boarding
school Kohate or something University? People know?
Choate? Choate, excuse me. So yeah. Anyway, so we know sadly the
עריות arayos to be much more lasting. Anyway, let's take a look.
The גמרא says like this.
I mean I guess if you talk about a case of let's
say נידה, nidda, that's just between the couple or whatever, that would
be a case where it'll be אפשר בתשובה efshar bitshuva and you
wouldn't be have, you know, wouldn't be anything beyond that. Okay, so
anyway the גמרא says like this. אמר רבי לוי קשה גזל הדיוט
יותר מגזל גבוה. Amar Rabbi Levi kasha gezel hedyot yoteir mgezel gavoha.
So again, same type of a point. We tend to treat that
anything having to do with ritual or God is a weightier sin,
but no, when you steal from a lay person it's worse than
stealing from God. שזה הקדים חטא למעילה וזה הקדים מעילה לחטא. shezeh
hikdim cheit lme'ila vezeh hikdim me'ila lcheit.
Because when you steal from a person, it says, you know, בכחש
בעמיתו בפקדון או בתשומת יד או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו, bchichesh
bamito bpikadon o btsumas yad o bgazel o ashaq et amito, and
then the I think the end of it it says what where
וכחש בעמיתו vchichesh bamito and then in the end it says something
somewhere, oh it says כי תחטא ומעלה מעל בהשם וכחש בעמיתו. ki
tichta umal ma'al baHashem vchichesh bamito. You're מועל mo'el by God and
then you and then it says and then it says that you
sinned. Okay. So why is that different? Whereas by doing מעילה me'ila
with God it says כי תמעול מעל וחטאה בשגגה. ki timol ma'al
vchat'a bishgaga.
Wait wait hold on. Okay no hold on I got okay here
it says okay I'm getting myself confused. When it says when you
steal from somebody it says נפש כי תחטא ומעלה מעל בהשם. nefesh
ki techeta uma'ala ma'al baHashem.
So first you חטא cheit and then there's a concept of מעילה,
me'ila, whereas by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it says נפש כי
תמעול מעל מקדשי השם מקדשי
השם nefesh ki timol ma'al mikodshei Hashem mikodshei Hashem and then and
then somewhere later it speaks about חטא. cheit. So now so okay
that's interesting but which would you say is worse? I don't know,
if you asked me מעילה me'ila is a, this is exactly maybe
the point, because מעילה me'ila is a religious concept. So to me
I think that that's worse, that it says מעילה me'ila first and
חטא cheit later. But he's saying no, here, the word מעילה me'ila
the way the רשבם Rashbam explains it means that you derived benefit.
So here you חטא cheit immediately, even before you've already sinned right
up front. And then the מעילה me'ila the deriving benefit comes later.
But the חטא cheit comes right up front. Whereas here from הקדש
hekdesh until you actually have derived benefit the חטא cheit will only
come later. So the חטא cheit comes earlier when you do it
between a person than when you do it with הקדש. hekdesh. Okay,
that's the way it's being read. וזה הקדים מעילה לחטא. vezeh hikdim
me'ila lcheit. ואמר רבי לוי בוא וראה שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא
מדת בשר ודם. V'amar Rabbi Levi bo re'eh shelo kemiddas HaKadosh Baruch
Hu middas basar vadam. Come see that God's ways are not the
ways of flesh and blood. הקדוש ברוך הוא ברכן לישראל בעשרים ושנים
וקללן בשמונה. HaKadosh Baruch Hu beirchan lYisrael b'esrim ushnayim v'kilelan bishmonah.
He blessed Israel with 22, which does not mean 22 פסוקים psukim
but means 22 letters, the letters of the Hebrew alphabet, and he
cursed them only with eight. Like he blessed them from A to
Z and he only cursed them from like A to H or
whatever, I don't know how many eight letters are in the English
alphabet. Okay what did that mean? ברכן בעשרים ושנים beirchan b'esrim ushnayim
because this is true right, the ברכות brachas and the קללות, klalos,
the גמרא does this in multiple places, it compares the ברכות brachas
and the קללות klalos at the end of ויקרא Vayikra to those
at the end of דברים. Devarim. And those at the end of
ויקרא, Vayikra, right, the קללות klalos are much shorter. Those at the
end of דברים, Devarim, the קללות klalos are much longer. So at
times the גמרא says, you know, that human beings are less forgiving
than God, so when משה Moshe spoke about the קללות klalos at
the end of דברים, Devarim, he had much much longer קללות. klalos.
So here it's making the same point but doing it with the
first letter and the last letter of the ברכות brachas and the
קללות. klalos. So in ויקרא Vayikra it says אם בחקתי תלכו, im
bchukosai telechu,
if you go in my edicts, and the end of the ברכות
brachas is קוממיות kommiyut which ends with a תיו. taf. So the
ברכות brachas go
from אלף לתיו. aleph to taf. Okay וקללן בשמונה v'kilelan bishmonah and
he cursed them only with eight, מאם בחקתי תמאסו mi've'im bchukosai tima'asu
which is a וו, vav, it starts with a וו, vav, עד
ואת חקתי געלה נפשם ad v'es chukosai ga'alah nafsham ends with a
מם. mem. So from וו vav to מם mem is only eight
letters. So the קללות klalos were only a third of the alphabet
and the ברכות... brachas... or A to Z. ואילו משה רבינו V'Ilu
Moshe Rabbeinu ברכן בשמונה birchan b'shmona וקללן בעשרים ושתיים, v'killelan b'esrim u'shtayim,
it's the reverse. ברכן בשמונה birchan b'shmona מוהיה אם שמוע תשמעו, mi'V'Haya
Im Shamoa Tishme'u, it will be if you listen, starts with a
ואו vav עד לעבדם, ad l'avdam, same ואו vav to a מם.
mem. Okay, so the ברכות brachos from ואו vav to מם mem
only a third of the alphabet. וקללן בעשרים ושתיים v'killelan b'esrim u'shtayim
מוהיה אם לא תשמעו, mi'V'Haya Im Lo Tishme'u, if you don't listen,
starts with a ואו vav עד ואין קונה, ad v'ein koneh, ends
with a הא. hei. So the ואו vav right goes back around
to the הא, hei, it's all twenty-two letters. Okay, so very nice.
Now before we end for today, I want to just read a
very fascinating תוספות, Tosafot, because here if take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot וקללן בעשרים ושתיים. v'killelan b'esrim u'shtayim. תוספות says מוהיה אם
לא תשמעו, mi'V'Haya Im Lo Tishme'u, מכאן נראה לי לפי פירוש רבנו
נסים, mikan nireh li l'fi peirush Rabbeinu Nissim, go to explain האי
דמחלקים וילך וניצבים hai d'mechalkim Vayeilech u'Nitzavim כשתי שבתות k'shei shabbosos between
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah to סוכות Succot בלא יום טוב, b'lo yom
tov, אף על פי שהיא פרשה קטנה, af al pi she'hi parsha
ketana, ומחברים מטות ומסעי u'mechabrim Matot u'Masei שגדולה יותר. she'gedola yoter. Right,
why is it sometimes we put מטות ומסעי Matot u'Masei together and
וילך Vayeilech and ניצבים Nitzavim apart? Like וילך Vayeilech and ניצבים Nitzavim
are so short, better keep them together and keep מטות ומסעי Matot
u'Masei apart. So he says, what's the explanation? He says, היינו משום
דבעינן שיתמו שנה וקללותיה. hainu mishum d'ba'inan she'yitmu shana u'klaloteiha.
What we want to do is we want to actually get, he
says, ניצבים Nitzavim before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Because when the year
ends, right, before the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of the new year,
you want to end the קללות. klalos. And there are still some
קללות klalos in ניצבים, Nitzavim, because you know, ניצבים Nitzavim continues with
the theme of the bad things, שיש קללות באתם ניצבים, she'yesh klalos
b'Atem Nitzavim, ואינו רוצים שיכנסו תוכחות כל שנה שעברה בשנה הבאה. v'einu
rotzim she'yichnesu tochachot kol shana she'avra b'shana haba'ah. Okay,
so that's a nice explanation. We want to get make sure ניצבים
Nitzavim comes before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So in order to do
that, we're going to have to combine מטות ומסעי Matot u'Masei and
separate ניצבים Nitzavim and וילך. Vayeilech. He says, no, דהכא משמע דלא
קרי קללות אלא באם בחוקותי וכי תבוא, de'hacha mashma d'lo kari klalos
ela b'Im Bechukotai v'Ki Tavo, דקאמר אם לא תשמעו עד ואין קונה.
d'ka'amar im lo tishme'u ad v'ein koneh. But
this דרשה drasha here sounds like the קללות klalos ended at the
end of כי תבוא. Ki Tavo. So you know, I don't know
why it's so terrible to have one category of קללות, klalos, but
they still extend into ניצבים, Nitzavim, but he says, you know, that
doesn't fully, this גמרא sounds like the real קללות klalos are כי
תבוא. Ki Tavo. So there wouldn't be a problem having ניצבים Nitzavim
after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So then why do we do it?
אבל משם ואילך לא חשיבי קללות, aval misham v'eilach lo chashivei klalos,
אבל נראה לי דלהכי אנו קוראים לעולם אתם ניצבים לפני ראש השנה,
aval nireh li de'lahachi anu korim l'olam Atem Nitzavim lifnei Rosh Hashanah,
כדי להפסיק בפרשה בין קללות דשנה שעברה דכי תבוא לשנה הבאה. k'dei
l'hafsik b'parsha bein klalos d'shana she'avra d'Ki Tavo l'shana haba'ah. Okay, and
then
so he says, it's the same idea but with a little twist.
We want to make sure that the קללות klalos ended and that
there was even a פרשה parsha to separate them. So כי תבוא
Ki Tavo was two weeks before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so the
week before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah we actually had a break between
the קללות klalos and starting the next year. What? A buffer. A
buffer. And now one last thing, because this is now relevant to
us, where שבועות Shavuot is now on our minds after we're done
with... ניצבים Nitzavim as being the תוכחה? tochacha? כי תבוא Ki Tavo
is the primary תוכחה. tochacha. That's the primary תוכחה, tochacha, but the
רבנו נסים Rabbeinu Nissim said there's still elements of תוכחה tochacha in
ניצבים. Nitzavim. No, it's a buffer, but we want the buffer from
in the previous year. And now relevant to us coming up, it
says, וכל כך נמי לעולם אנו קוראים במדבר לפני עצרת, v'chol kach
nami l'olam anu korim Bamidbar lifnei Atzeret, כדי להפסיק בין קללות דאם
בחוקותי לעצרת, k'dei l'hafsik bein klalos d'Im Bechukotai l'Atzeret, שהוא ראש השנה
לפירות האילן. she'hu Rosh Hashanah l'peirot ha'ilan.
And therefore we want to always make sure במדבר Bamidbar comes before
שבועות Shavuot so that the קללות klalos at the end of ויקרא
Vayikra don't run right up against שבועות. Shavuot. שבועות Shavuot is also
a type of a יום הדין yom hadin for the new fruit,
so we want there to be a buffer between the קללות klalos
and the new year, the new year of the fruit. כדתנן במסכת
מגילה דתקן עזרא קללות שבמשנה תורה קודם לעצרת. k'detnan b'masechet Megilla d'tikein
Ezra klalos she'b'mishneh Torah kodem l'Atzeret.
Okay, so very nice little thing to appreciating some aspects of the
liturgy and of the way the פרשיות parshiot are arranged.